<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of the right honble the Lady Frances Paget, the religious consort of the right honble William Lord Paget, (eldest daughter to the right honourable Henry Earl of Holland, who was beheaded for his loyalty to this King) in the parish-church of West-Drayton in the county of Middlesex, on the 12th of Nevember, 1672. By Jehu Jenny, M.A. and Vicar of Harmondsworth.</title>
            <author>Jenney, John, d. 1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46825</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J673A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220733</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832125</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832125</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36596</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46825)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36596)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1779:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of the right honble the Lady Frances Paget, the religious consort of the right honble William Lord Paget, (eldest daughter to the right honourable Henry Earl of Holland, who was beheaded for his loyalty to this King) in the parish-church of West-Drayton in the county of Middlesex, on the 12th of Nevember, 1672. By Jehu Jenny, M.A. and Vicar of Harmondsworth.</title>
                  <author>Jenney, John, d. 1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.D. for Nevil Simmons at the Princes Arms in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Paget, Frances Paget, --  Lady, d. 1672.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36596:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36596:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED At the FUNERAL of the Right Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> the Lady Frances Paget, The religious Conſort of the right Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> 
               <hi>William</hi> Lord PAGET, (Eldeſt Daughter to the Right Honourable <hi>Henry</hi> Earl of <hi>Holland,</hi> who was beheaded for his Loyalty to his King) In the Pariſh-Church of <hi>Weſt-Drayton</hi> in the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> on the 12th of <hi>November,</hi> 1672.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JEHU JENNY,</hi> M. A. and Vicar of <hi>Harmondſworth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for <hi>Nevil Simmons</hi> at the Princes Arms in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:36596:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36596:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE William Lord PAGET, Baron of Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſert, Knight of the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Order of the Bath, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Othing but your Lordſhips Commands could have forced into the Light this Diſcourſe of ſo haſty conception, and they give ſome countenance to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of this Dedication, otherwiſe I am too conſcious that nothing of mine can deſerve the Patronage of ſo great a Name
<pb facs="tcp:36596:3"/>or Title; nor do I hope for Acceptance of this Service, further than it is a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of my Obedience, and bears ſome (though faint) Characters of your late dear Conſort. That the Piety and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of that excellent Lady may ſtill live in your Noble Family (of which there are viſible hopes largely promiſing) and conſequently the Bleſſing of it on your Poſterity reach the utmoſt extent of the Promiſe to ſuch Obedience, ſhall be a conſiderable part of the conſtant Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt Obſequious Chaplain,</hi> Jehu Jenny.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="funeral_sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:36596:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATTH. 24.46.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Bleſſed is that Servant, whom his Lord when he cometh ſhall find ſo doing.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR Man to know God and himſelf, is the Comprehenſion of his whole Duty. The Poet could tell us of the latter, that it is that Wiſdom which is from above, from Heaven heavenly; that which will tranſ-element us, have that happy influence to ſublimate us into that which is coeleſtial, make us partakers or the Divine Nature, and at length when we ſhall be ripen'd and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently refin'd, tranſlate us to the enjoyments of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Thus for Man to underſtand himſelf, to know what he is, will make him new create him what he is not, and render him happy in that degree to which without this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge he could never attain. And upon this notice, this diſcovery, who thirſts not after ſo much Goodneſs, followed with ſo great Reward? who is not impatiently eager on the ſtudy of this Philoſophers Stone? who will not judge it thrifty prodigality to lay out all to purchaſe this Pearl of ſo great price? to any conſiderate man this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt needs be matter of his higheſt ſatisfaction, this acquirement is a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36596:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>recompence infinitly beyond all his labour and ſeverity: in the ſearch after which there is no befooling darkneſs, no diſcouraging difficulty, no climbing the Clouds, or croſſing the Sea for it, but this word of Wiſdom is <hi>nigh thee, Deut.</hi> 30.12, 13, 14. 'tis plain and eaſie, that which God hath ſent down to us; nay, which the Son of God, when for us men and for our Salvation he came down from Heaven, himſelf hath delivered to us, that which in the Text he preach'd to his Diſciples, and in them to us all, in which he hath ſatisfied the Pſalmiſt's queſtion, <hi>What is man?</hi> what is man, but a Servant to the great Lord? and in this given a further re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to the inquiry of thoſe <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>Souldiers, Luke</hi> 3. and who elſe ſhall come with the like caſe, <hi>Maſter, what muſt we do?</hi> if Servants, what's our work, our imployment? He informs them, to be deligent in their Office; and to whet them to this, he lets them know, that he himſelf will have an eye over them, and take an account of them, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them to all this, that as he findes them to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſo ſhall they be looked by him, enjoy his favour, the fulleſt bleſſedneſs; <hi>Bleſſed, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in this ſhort account of the words, I have given you the Parts of my Text, which are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">I. In what capacity man ſtands here, he is a Servant, <hi>That Servant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. As ſuch, what is his employment, expreſt in theſe words, <hi>ſo doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. The account will be taken of him, the Lord of the family will come to take it himſelf, though it be intimated, that the time when he will come is very uncertain.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. The reward of that Servant, that ſhall be found faithful and deligent; <hi>Bleſſed is that Servant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of each of theſe with as much brevity as the Subject will allow.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:36596:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="1">I. In what capacity man ſtands here, he is a Servant, <hi>That Servant.</hi> God made man, but made him not for nought; but to the excellency of his endowments in the deſign of Heaven was proportion'd an employment for him. The Schools maintained this Axiome, <hi>Quicquid agit, agit prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter finem,</hi> that whatſoever moves in the nature of an Agent, deſigns ſomething as the end of its acting. And certainly this perfection muſt be eminently in the Author of Nature, and no end can we define worthy his propoſal, but his own Glory in the manifeſtations of his Power, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs; the moſt learned Philoſopher and the greateſt Divine that ever was in the World, affirms this of the great work of Creation, <hi>Pro.</hi> 16.4. <hi>The Lord hath made all things for himſelf: yea even the Wicked for the day of evil.</hi> That diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly improfitable part of the Creation <hi>Telluris inutile pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> as the Poet ſpeaks, the wicked (though God made them not ſo, he made man upright, and left him <hi>in the hands of his own counſel, as the Son of</hi> Sirach, <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 15.14. yet) his over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling Wiſdom makes them ſerve the deſigns of his inflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Juſtice, becauſe they will not pay that homage they owe to their Maker, but refuſe to be happy, and ſo defeat the purpoſes of enthroning his Mercy, therefore he obliges them to wait on the triumph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of his Vengance as the juſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merit of their obſtinacy and rebellion. In the 1ſt <hi>of Geneſis laſt verſe,</hi> when the Ahnighty ſurveys the workmanſhip of his fix dayes creation, he gives his approbation: <hi>God ſaw every thing that he had made, and behold it was very good.</hi> Good in this reſpect among others, in regard of that the God of order had placed in this large family of the Creation, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotting each part its ſtation, and aſſigning them operations according to what powers and faculties he had implanted in them, ſo that from the Seraphim to the Piſmire there is no creature but what in a larger or leſs capacity is a Servant of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36596:5"/>its Creator. The Philoſopher could ſay that all things do ſerve in his notion the firſt Being and Cauſe of all things; which is one of the meditations of the Royal Pſalmiſt, which he hath left us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.89, 90, 91. where he enumerates particulars: <hi>For ever, O Lord, thy Word is ſetled in Heaven. Thy Faithfulneſs is unto all Generations: thou haſt eſtabliſhed the Earth, and it abideth. They continue this day according to thine Ordinances.</hi> And then he concludes, <hi>For all are thy Servants.</hi> And upon enquiry we ſhall find his aſſertion true. Do but lift up your eyes to the Heavens, and as the Prince of the Philoſophers affirms them to be in perpetual motion; ſo he that was a Prince as well as a Philoſopher, obſerves that they move in that Sphere which their all-wiſe Framer fixt them in. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.1. <hi>The Heavens declare the Glory of God.</hi> And if we behold the Sun, it confutes <hi>Copernicus, Rejoyceth as a ſtrong man to run his race,</hi> v. 5. Should I take you up into the third Heaven, the Heaven of Heavens, the Angels there are <hi>miniſtring Spirits, Heh.</hi> 1. <hi>ult.</hi> Angels and Arch-Angels, and all the company of Heaven, all the Orders of that Celeſtial Hierarchy, they <hi>do God's Commandments, and execute his pleaſure, Pſal.</hi> 103.20, 21. If we look upon the creatures here below, they bear a part in this ſervice, the Sea hath the boundary of God's decree for its ebbing and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; hitherto ſhalt thou extend thy proud waves and no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: the moſt inconſiderable inferiour particles of the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, the Snow, and Vapour, and Stormy-Wind are ſaid to <hi>fulfil his Word,</hi> Pſal. 148.8. So that this relation of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants the Angels thoſe heavenly Courtiers diſdain not, and the lower parts of the World are not too mean for an Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in; then certainly Man the Lord of this ſublimary World can upon no account plead exemption, he is a ſervant. But as the Apoſtle uſes the compariſon touching the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.42. <hi>One Star differeth from another Star in glory.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:36596:5"/>or as the ſame Apoſtle expreſſes it, <hi>In a great houſe thee are not only veſſels of gold and ſilver, but alſo of wood and earth.</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20. ſo t'is here in the large Houſe-hold of the ſupernal and lower world, each ſervant hath his province &amp; employment ſet him ſuitable to thoſe capacities, by which he is inabled to make a diſcharge of his duty, which what Man's is, is a ſeaſonable enquiry; and,</p>
            <p n="2">II. The ſecond part of the text. As a Servant what is mans employment expreſt in theſe words, <hi>ſo doing.</hi> Man hath a work to do, but what it is you cannot imagine in that little ſcantling of time allotted for this exerciſe I ſhould fully diſcourſe to you, the doing the particulars of which will take up our whole lives, did they never ſo far exceed Davids ſumme of them. It is to doe the work which God hath ſet us and ſent us into the world to do, briefly 'tis doing the works of our general and particular calling.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The works of our general calling as Chriſtians. And here the Chriſtian is obliged to the obſervance of that divine precept. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. <hi>To render to all their dues.</hi> And the duties of our general calling are reducible to theſe three heads, which the Apoſtle gives us in charge, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12. <hi>To live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this preſent world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To begin with our duty to him, who is the beginning of all things, and Lord of the family. And this we are early call'd upon by the wiſeman to make a diſcharge of. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Remember now thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth.</hi> He that gave us our being, provides for our well-being, and hath contriv'd our being happy, (unleſs we our ſelves fruſtrate the deſign) may upon all accounts challenge a grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervice and homage, there being nothing in the world more rational then Religion and the Worſhip of a Deity. And here the Chriſtian hath a large task of duty, the performance of all internal and external acts of Piety and Devotion, the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36596:6"/>maintaining alwaies a reverential dread and fear of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty, to adore that incomprehenſible Being, to demean our ſelves ſo towards God, as may beſt comport with thoſe Divine attributes of his purity and power, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and goodneſs, ſincerely and conſcientiouſly to perform all external acts of Religion, all duties of divine worſhip and ſervice, to hear and pray, meditate and receive, and what elſe in the whole duty of man God requires of us, as his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate worſhip. This is to live <hi>godly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Righteouſly,</hi> towards our fellow-Servants. To love my Neighbour as my ſelf, to obſerve that golden rule, ſo much admired by the Heathen, ſo little practiſed by the Chriſtian, ſo fully taught in the old and new Teſtament, ſo frequently preſt by Prophets and Apoſtles, and inculcated by our Bleſſed Lord, <hi>Whatſoever we would that men ſhould do unto us, we ſhould do the ſame to them.</hi> To do juſtice and to love mercy, to make our ſelves friends of the Mammon of unrighteouſneſs, to diſtribute to the neceſſities of the poor, to do good to all men, by good counſel and a ſuitable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation to perſwade as many as we can to be holy and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and to ſave their ſouls, to reprove our offending Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to bear with the infirmities of thoſe that are weak, to comfort thoſe that mourn, to exhort one another to day, while it is called to day, to do as our Bleſſed Lord did, when he was upon the earth, whoſe buſineſs it was to go about, and ſeek all opportunities of doing good, <hi>Acts.</hi> 10.38.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Soberly.</hi> To have ſo much regard to our ſelves as to do nothing unworthy of that place in Gods family he hath ſet us in. To obſerve all rules and precepts of ſobriety, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance and chaſtity. Some of the heathen Philoſophers have diſſwaded from ſome debaucheries, as indecencies &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts offer'd to humane Nature, but the Chriſtian hath high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er motives for all ſobriety of converſation; to reverence our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36596:6"/>humane nature as united to the Divine in the perſon of Chriſt, and ſo to preſerve it from all ſpot and defilement, as he did when he was veſted with our fleſh here below; to look upon our bodies as Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, and ſo not to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them to be ſinks of ſin and neſts of all uncleanneſs: and laſtly, to think what they ſhall be in their glorified eſtate after the reſurrection, that ſo when Chriſt ſhall come to work that mighty change upon them, he may not find them in the worſt ſenſe vile, that is, ſinful bodies. To do all this, and ſo to do it, as to be ſaluted with an <hi>Euge</hi> for our well-doing, may well be thought no eaſy task, but that which will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire all Chriſtian diligence and circumſpection, ſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem the time, as to fill up every part of it with the proper duties of it, and yet after all this one thing is ſtill wanting which is, —</p>
            <p n="2">2. To be diligent in our particular Callings, that ſtate and condition of life to which God hath call'd each of us, as ſome to be Magiſtrates, ſome Miniſters, ſome Merchants, ſome Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Command of God to earn our bread in the ſweat of our brows, the prevention of idleneſs, the obligation of providing for our families, God's diſtribution of ſeveral gifts, the benefit of humane ſociety and the Weal-publick, beſpeak the neceſſity of ſome Calling or other for every man to employ and buſie himſelf in. Here perhaps there may be ſome will cenſure my diſcourſe to be ungentile, and that I maintain a paradox to affirm, as I do, that every man muſt labour in ſome calling or other; if you bring up this levelling humour, where's the Gentleman? was not he born like that <hi>Leviathan Job</hi> ſpeaks of, only to <hi>take his paſtime in the World?</hi> But a Reverend and modeſt<note n="†">The Author of the <hi>whole Duty of Man.</hi>
               </note> Author hath made it out to be no Soloeciſm to aſſert a Gentleman to have a Calling, the orderly diſpoſal of his Family, the preſerving what in him lyes peace
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36596:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>among his Neighbours, the influencing all he converſes with by a good example will not ſuffer him to be an exception to this general rule, that every man in the world hath a Calling, and to be diligent in it is every mans duty, and that which is highly juſtifiable: for the husband-man to be at his plough the trades-man in his ſhop, the ſchollar at his book, is to be <hi>ſo doing.</hi> But here we muſt obſerve a double caution.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That our general and particular Calling do not juſtle out or enterfere upon the duties of each other. The wiſe Steward renders to each his portion in due ſeaſon. It is a ſin for me to be in the market or in a worſe place, when I ſhould be at the Church; and on the other hand, an indiſcreet zeal muſt not make me neglect my Calling and to provide for my family; ſuch a profeſſion renders me worſe than an infidel.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt be ſure keep within the bounds of our particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Calling for which we have an expreſs command. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.24. <hi>Let every man, wherein he is called, therein abide with God.</hi> He that holds the plough muſt not touch the Ark, the Apron and the Ephod, the Shop and the Pulpit are diſtinct, unleſs our Mechanick Preachers can confute St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith, that <hi>all are not Prophets, nor all Apoſtles, nor all Teachers.</hi> The motion of a Chriſtian muſt not be excentrick, he muſt keep within bounds. No man can climb the Throne or the Pulpit without a warrant from God, leſt it be ſaid to him, as the Egyptian to <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Who made thee a Prince, a Judge over us?</hi> who made thee a Preacher? for <hi>No man taketh this honour unto himſelf, but he that is called of God, as was Aaron, Heb.</hi> 5.4.</p>
            <p>Thus have I with all imaginable brevity gone through the ſeveral parts of mans duty, ſhewed him what it is the Lord doth require of him, to do juſtly, to love mercy, to be ſober and temperate, and walk humbly with his God. So that by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36596:7"/>way of Application you will eaſily infer with me.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That 'tis not <hi>nihil agendo, doing nothing.</hi> Idleneſs is the Devils anvil, on which he hammers us into any ſhape of vice or wickedneſs, 'tis a tempting of the Tempter, a giving him the opportunity of throwing a temptation in our way, and therefore it was St. <hi>Hieromes</hi> advice to be alwaies buſied, to prevent the Devils having this advantage over us. <hi>Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per boni aliquid operis facito, ut Diabolus te ſemper inveniat occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patum.</hi> Had <hi>David</hi> been in the Camp or at Council-table, when he walkt on the battlements of his houſe, <hi>Bathſheba</hi> had waſht her ſelf without defiling <hi>uriahs</hi> bed. Man is of an active nature, if he be doing nothing, he will quickly be doing ſomething he ſhould not. Nor,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is it <hi>nil boni agendo, doing that which is as good as nothing.</hi> To ſpend a morning <hi>inter ſpeculum et pectinem,</hi> our eyes would ake and our hands grow weary, ſhould a Prayer-Book be our entertainment but a third part of that time the comb and the glaſſe take us up. One meal conſumes as much of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious time as <hi>Luther</hi> ſpent of the whole day in prayer, which was three houres. <hi>Stratonitus</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Rhoudians,</hi> that they built houſes as if they were immortal, but feaſted as if they were to live but a little while; we who dwell in houſes of clay, feaſt as if we were immortal, no life beyond this, as if the indulging our ſenſual appetites were the higheſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of our reaſonable nature, and the <hi>hoc agere</hi> of a Chriſtian. An empty viſit, wherein our entertainment is an idle and uncharitable cenſure of the actions of others, and a debaucht Theatre ſhare the reſt of the day. Than theſe the Emperours pricking of flies will be found a buſie idleneſs more innocent. Nor,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Is it <hi>male agendo, doing that which is worſe than nothing,</hi> doing evil, committing ſin. This is the Devil's work, and as he ſets them to work, from him they muſt expect their wages,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36596:8"/>which what it is the Apoſtle lets them know beforehand. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. <hi>The wages of ſin is eternal death.</hi> This will not paſs in the account, it will not be well our Lord ſhould find us ſo doing if he doth, we ſhall have ſmall thanks for our pains. Which minds me of the third general of the text.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The account will be taken of him, the Lord of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily will come to take it himſelf, though it be intimated, that the time when he will come is very uncertain. Here we muſt know that there is a particular and a general coming of our Lord to Judgement. His particular coming to Judgment is on every one in particular at the hour of death, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Then ſhall the duſt return to the earth as it was: and the ſpirit ſhall return unto God who gave it.</hi> Where by the return of the ſoul to God, we muſt underſtand its giving up an account of all its actions done in the fleſh, whether good or evil; as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly as the Body at death returns to its earthly Mother to be diſſolved, ſo aſſuredly the ſoul returnes to its heavenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be judged. The general coming of Chriſt ſhall be at the laſt day, when the dead bodies ſhall ariſe out of their graves, and both ſoul and body receive the ſentence of abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution or condemnation. <hi>John.</hi> 5.29. <hi>All that are in the graves ſhall come forth, they that have done good, unto the reſurrection of life, and they that have done evil, unto the reſurrection of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> This latter is a ratification and publication of the former, and a more full collation or infliction of reward or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. Each of thoſe Advents of our Lord are certain, but the time of them very uncertain,</p>
            <p n="1">1. His particular coming to Judgment is certain, which is at the hour of death. There is a Decree for this paſt and ſign'd in Heaven. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. <hi>It is appointed for all Men once to die.</hi> And you know what follows that, And this Decree is irreverſible like the Laws of the <hi>Medes and Perſians.</hi> Deaths vaſt ſpoils and large triumphs ſufficiently prove its
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36596:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>univerſal Empire. 'Tis not to purpoſe to inſiſt upon this, when there's ſcarce any man living will ſhew himſelf ſo little a man, as to queſtion whether he be mortal. The wiſe and the fool, the King and the Subject, the Paſtor and his Flock, the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and the vile Perſon, the Rich man and the Beggar, all muſtly down in the duſt, and <hi>make their bed,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>in the darkneſs.</hi> But though there be an appointed time for this great and laſt change of man, yet when that time will come is very uncertain. Thoſe infinite diſeaſes and ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ualties to which the life of man is incident &amp; ſo eaſily cut the thread of it, fully evince that there is nothing more certain then the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of the hour of death. One dies in his nonage, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſtrength and vigour of his years, and another in a full age: one in his bed, and another in the field. <hi>Hodie mihi, cras tibi.</hi> The Bell went for ſuch a one laſt, but who ſhall go next God knows. To any of us that are here in health this hour, that for all we know before the next it may be ſaid as St. <hi>Peter to Sapphira, Acts. 5.</hi> Behold the feet of them which brought this honorable Perſon to her grave, are ready to bear thee to the ſame place. And therfore tis a point of the greateſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to conſider our latter end and prepare for it, ſince its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is ſo uncertain. And perhaps in this caſe, that advice of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was not amiſs, to him that deſired to know when was the beſt time to repent and reform his life in, to whom he gave this anſwer, that it was ſafeſt to do that the day before he died, which was that preſent day for any thing he was aſſured of the contrary.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As his particular coming at the hour of death is certain, ſo is his laſt coming at the end of the World. <hi>The ſon of man ſhall come in his glory, and all his holy Angels with him, and ſhall ſit upon the Throne of his glory. Mat.</hi> 25.31. <hi>And then we muſt all appear before the Judgment-ſeat of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in his Body, according to that he hath
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36596:9"/>done, whether it be good or bad,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> hath deſcribed this day with its attendant circumſtances. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. <hi>The day of the Lord will come, in the which the Heavens ſhall paſs away with a great noiſe, and the elements ſhall melt with fervent heat, the earth alſo and the works that are therein ſhall be burnt up.</hi> This is an Article of our faith, that Chriſt will come to judge the quick and the dead, and is a deduction in Divinity that the belief of a God and of his providence and government of the world doth neceſſarily infer. But of that day and hour, when this judgment ſhall paſs on the whole world, knoweth no man. Our Lord hath told us, that this his coming will be as a thief in the night, to allarm us to ſtand upon our guard and watch, that we be not guilty of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>providence, and ſo overtaken with the ſurprize of the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Virgins: We have the Doctrine of Chriſts coming, and the uſe we ſhould make of it both laid down by our Bleſſed Saviour in the 42. <hi>v.</hi> of this <hi>cb. Watch therefore, for you know not what hour your Lord doth come.</hi> And again <hi>verſ.</hi> 44. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be ye alſo ready: for in ſuch an hour you think not, the ſon of man cometh.</hi> There have indeed been ſome ſo bold as to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to define thoſe times and ſeaſons which the Father hath put in his own power, and to pretend to a diſcovery of the <hi>Arcana Imperil</hi> of Heaven, among the reſt to determine when this day ſhall be; but in that time hath overcome and outworn ſeveral their computations, the preſumption of their folly needs no other confutation.</p>
            <p>To preſs you to that which is the natural reſult of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, diligence and faithfulneſs in doing your duty, I ſhall only urge you with a double conſideration about this coming of our Lord.</p>
            <p n="1">I. It will be a ſevere and ſtrict account our Lord will take of us when he comes. He will bring every work into judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with <hi>every ſecret thing, Eccles.</hi> 12.14. All our irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36596:9"/>and prophaneſs, our injuſtice and oppreſſion, our intemperance and uncleanneſs. There will be no impoſing on him, no prevaricating with him, no palliating any fault, cloaking it from him, before whom <hi>all things are naked and open. Heb.</hi> 4.13. Indeed if we be found faithful, and that in the maine we are not tardy, God will overlook (I do not ſay he ſees not, but) he will paſs by our failings and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, our humane frailties. But there be two things, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which if we be found guilty of, it will go hard with us inſtead of an <hi>euge</hi> we ſhall have an <hi>apage.</hi> Hypocriſie or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> and Inſincerity in his Service, whatſoever we do, we muſt do it <hi>heartily, as to the Lord.</hi> The heart is the chief part of the Sacrifice, which if it be wanting, God loaths the Oblation, be it never ſo Coſtly. <hi>To love the Lord our God with all the Heart, with all the Soul, and with all the Mind, is the firſt and great Commandment of the Law, Mat.</hi> 22.37, 38. To bow and cringe in the Temple, as the <hi>Syrian</hi> in the houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> and the heart to be at a diſtance, is a Service f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>r for ſuch a blind Idol, than an <hi>all-ſeeing, heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearching God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Partiality,</hi> A moſt unhappy error men are willing to deceive themſelves with, they think to do the will of God in a Figure will ſerve the turn, and ſo give him a part for the whole. If they are Zealous and forward in his Service and Worſhip, he will wink at their Injuſtice and Oppreſſion, or if I am open-handed I may be wicked-hearted; an Alms ſhall diſpenſe for my Uncleanneſs, my Loyalty atone for my Impiety and Debauchery; if I have heapt up an Eſtate by indirect means and unrighteous practiſes, to build a ſmall Hoſpital, or bequeath a petty Legacy to the Poor will ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the whole lump of ill-gotten goods, and effect my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for all my wickedneſs. But God delivered to us the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36596:10"/>whole Decalogue, and for the whole he will account with us. I'm ſure we ſhall never enter into the Kingdom of Heaven with a maimed obedience. If at the laſt day we ſhall plead any of this, the good deeds we have done, and think that they will expiate for whatſoever elſe we have omitted, Chriſt will reply to us as to the <hi>Phariſees; Theſe ought ye to have done, and not have left the other undone. David's</hi> confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence was onely in a Catholick Obedience, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6. <hi>Then ſhall I not be aſhamed, when I have reſpect unto all thy Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Sentence that will be then paſt is final and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſive beyond any appeal or rehearing. An error here is of moſt unhappy conſequence, there is no place for a ſecond. We ſhall then be adjudged either to an happy or a diſmal Eternity, to everlaſting life or endleſs puniſhment. Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Tears, Repentance and promiſes of amendment, which if ſincere, are in this life effectual for Mercy and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, will then be unavailable: ſo that indeed we have the Sentence of Life and Death within our ſelves, 'tis in our own choice whether we will be happy or miſerable to all eternity. Theſe two eſtates depend upon our acquitting our ſelves here in our Maſter's ſervice; if upon our Lord's ſeeming delay of his coming, we ſhall ſmite our fellow-ſervants, eat and drink with the drunken, be riotous and diſorderly in the family, what can we expect but to have our portion aſſign'd us with Hypocrites, where there ſhal be <hi>weeping and gnaſhing of teeth?</hi> On the other hand, if we are emulous of happineſs, and ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of our Lord's approbation, we muſt be faithful and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, work if we expect wages, abound in every good work of humility, ſobriety and charity; for with him it ſhall fare well, whom his Lord when he cometh ſhall find ſo doing, he ſhall recieve a bleſſing from the Lord. And this brings me to,</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:36596:10"/>
            <p n="4">4. The laſt part of the Text, the reward of that Servant that ſhall be found faithful and diligent; <hi>Bleſſed is that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant whom his Lord ſhall find ſo doing.</hi> And here two things offer themſelves to our conſideration. 1. The conſtancy and perſeverance of a Chriſtian in well-doing; <hi>whom his Lord ſhall find ſo doing.</hi> 2. His crown of reward for ſo doing; <hi>Bleſſed is that ſervant.</hi> But a word of each of theſe, and I have done.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The conſtancy and perſeverance of a Chriſtian in well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing; <hi>Whom his Lord &amp;c.</hi> 'Tis conſtancy crowns all our actions. He whoſe virtue like <hi>Ephraim's</hi> goodneſs, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13. evaporates and dwindles away, as the <hi>morning Cloud, and early dew,</hi> that will be baffled in his Chriſtian Courſe by a thwarting temptation, and grows weary of well doing, puts an affront upon Religion, &amp; is juſtly deprived the hopes of its reward. But he that amidſt the foul ſhocks of Satan and an evil world, abides like a rock in the Sea, ſtands immoveable as <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> he ſhall receive a <hi>Kingdom which cannot be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi> The devotion of a Chriſtian like the <hi>veſtal fire</hi> muſt burn continually, never go out, he muſt be like the Sun in the firmament fixt in his orb, and rejoyce as a Gyant to run his courſe, give ſhine in the world to the lateſt minute of his ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. The prize is at the end of a Chriſtian's race. We read indeed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. of ſome that came late into the vineyard, but of none that received the penny but thoſe that wrought in it till their Lord call'd them out. When St. <hi>Paul</hi> had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht his courſe then and not till then he could put forth his hand to receive the <hi>Crown of Righteouſneſs,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7, 8. If our Lord find us ſo doing he will pronounce us bleſſed.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The laſt particular, the crown of reward for ſo doing; <hi>Bleſſed is that Servant.</hi> Here 'tis not to be expected in the running of thoſe few ſands that are yet behind, I ſhould ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deſcribe the Bleſſedneſs of the Text. He that with the young man can truly ſay, <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nia haec obſervavi,</hi> he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36596:11"/>that doth theſe things with faithfulneſs and diligence, ſhall better underſtand this bleſſedneſs by a fruition of it, then by the largeſt account can be given of it, however allow me but in two words to give a ſhort and diſtant proſpect of this Holy Land, as it were to ſhew you a glimpſe of this happineſs. 'Tis to be able to meet the <hi>King of terrours</hi> without fear, to bid Death welcome as the meſſenger of happy tydings, to have the Soul enlarged from a priſon of ſin and ſorrow, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and temptation, to have a company of the Militia of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the Courtiers of the great King conduct and introduce us into the Royal Preſence, to have the whole Quire of Saints and Angels ſhout at our entrance, and welcome us into the joys of our Lord, to enjoy the pleaſures <hi>of the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect,</hi> to look back w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> amazing tranſport on that world of ſin and miſery we are reſcued from and have left behind us, thoſe vaſt rocks and dangers we eſcaped ſhipwracking on, to admire God's goodneſs, and praiſe him for it continually: and after all this, when the Harveſt is ripe, and the end of the world is come, and the conſummation of all things, to have our bodies at the reſurrection faſhioned like the glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, and be made a fit receptacle for the ſoul to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and for ever dwell in, <hi>to be caught up in the clouds, and meet the Lord in the air,</hi> to have our perſons pronounc'd righteous and innocent in the hearing of men and Angels, to ſit on the bench with Chriſt, to encompaſs his royal ſeat of Judicature and with him judge the world of wicked men; and after this grand Aſſize is over, to have a more ſolemn inaugration into bliſſe, each of us to take his place in the upper houſe, to be ſeated about the Throne of God, and there <hi>to be for ever with the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I carried you thorough the ſeveral parts of my Text, and at laſt brought you to the haven where you would
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36596:11"/>be, the haven of reſt, the higheſt Heavens. Let me now intreat you to take one turn in the valley of the ſhadow of death, whilſt I apply my diſcourſe, and you your meditation to this <hi>ſad Text</hi> before us. Of this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Perſon our deceaſed Siſter, and my ever honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Lady, I hope it is not expected, it may ſeem need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs for me to ſay much to you her Relations, Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and Acquaintance, to whom ſhe was ſo well known, and eſpecially in this place where her works ſo loudly praiſe her in the gates: I ſhall not therefore powr forth the whole Box, only ſhed a few drops of this precious Oyntment. Not to tell you that ſhe was deſcended of an antient and honourable Family, (though that be a thing not contemptible) this her juſt funeral Exequies declare better than I can; but <hi>vix ea noſtra voco,</hi> my task is to blazon a more noble Eſcutcheon, her Honours ſhe bears in the Herauldry of Heaven, her Vertues which were properly her own, and a more enobling nobility then that derived from her Anbeſtours. In her minority ſhe had (as I am well informed, and have good reaſon to believe) the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> and bleſſing of a vertuous and ſevere education, which early tincture left that reliſh, which verified wiſe <hi>Solomons</hi> maxime, <hi>Pro.</hi> 22.6. <hi>Train up a Child in the way he ſhould go: and when he is old, he will not depart from it.</hi> At an unuſual age (though mature in regard of her gravity and diſcretion) ſhe entred into a married eſtate, in which above fourty years ſhe was a moſt lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and loyal Conſort to her dear Lord, in which time ſhe had ſo fully ſtudied <hi>Solomons Oeconomicks,</hi> that her life was a moſt exact tranſcript of them; and without the leaſt flattery, I may ſay, her carriage in her dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Relations was the beſt Commentarie I ever met
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36596:12"/>with upon the 31 <hi>ch. of Proverbs, Solomons</hi> deſcription of a vertuous woman, and a good houſewife. If ever any woman had that ornament of a meek and quiet ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in her family, which St. <hi>Peter</hi> makes to be of ſo great price in the ſight of God, this good Lady had it. To her now diſconſolate Lord ſhe was ſuch a wife as <hi>Solomon</hi> deſcribes. <hi>Pro.</hi> 31.12. <hi>ſhe will do him good all the daies of her life;</hi> to her Children a tender and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Mother, to her Servants a loving and kind Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs.—But there were among many other three emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent vertues in this excellent Perſon, which ſhould I not mention, beſides a great injuſtice to the dead, in ſuffering her name to dye, I ſhould wrong the living of a worthy example, her Piety, her Charity, her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and Chriſtian Magnanimity.</p>
            <p n="1">I. I begin at the Houſe of God, where ſhe ſo delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be, her <hi>Piety.</hi> And in this ſhe was not new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fangled, as the Age, but old-faſhioned. Her Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was not a bare ſhew or an empty noiſe, only that of the tongue or an outſide paint, but her Piety was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid and ſubſtantial, even and uniform, that which exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it ſelf in the fruits of a good life. As to the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal acts of Divine Service and Worſhip, ſhe was moſt frequent in them, ſhe ſeldom took up with ſo little as <hi>David's</hi> morning, evening, and noon, but very often came up to the Pſalmiſt's higheſt Pitch of devotion, of praying to and praiſing of God ſeven times in the day; beſides her publique and cloſet-devotions, ſhe conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attended on the morning and evening ſacrifice of her family, in which ſhe gave a moſt eminent example: the ſticking of a pin, or the laying of a hair kept her not till the ſervice was half over, but her zeal for the ſervice of God made her careleſs of what habit or dreſs
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36596:12"/>ſhe came in, rather then ſtay away or come tardy; her exceeding devotion carried her to <hi>Davids</hi> pious option, to enjoy the <hi>Door-keepers</hi> place to be firſt in and laſt out of the Houſe of God. And truly ſhe was of <hi>Joſhua's</hi> ſociable temper, ſhe was for <hi>I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord.</hi> Her ſervants never met with greater diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure or more ſevere chiding from her than for the neglect of their duty to God.</p>
            <p n="2">II. As her <hi>Piety</hi> was great, ſo her <hi>Charity</hi> was large. As God had given her the riches of this world, ſo the knew full well that ſhe had more in her Cuſtody than was her own, the poor's portion; ſhe look't upon her ſelf as the Almighty's Almoner, and underſtood it his pleaſure ſhe ſhould diſpenſe bountifully. An empty belly, a naked back, or the ſores of an helpleſs La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar, were ſuch oratory as ever prevail'd for her relief. I am confident there be many here weeping, as the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows over <hi>Dorcas, Acts.</hi> 9. that can ſhew the coats and garments ſhe provided for them, and who were cloathed and fed by her bounty. She might juſtly have made the proteſtation of <hi>Job; If I have ſeen any periſh for want of cloathing, or any poor for want of covering: if his loynes have not bleſſed me, and if he were not warmed with the fleece of my ſheep, Job.</hi> 31.19.20. She was wiſe in her Charity, and underſtood her own intereſt well, and knew that ſuch ſowing brought in a plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful crop, a great encreaſe, that ſhe ſhould make a great return for all ſhe thus laid out, and ſhould be reimbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with an intereſt infinitely above the principal, when her Lord at the laſt day ſhall publiquely read her lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings out; <hi>Hungry, and ye fed me, thirſty, and ye gave me drink, naked, and ye cloathed me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Her <hi>Patience</hi> and Chriſtian Magnanimity. And
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36596:13"/>here I may well truly break forth in admiration, as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Father upon the ſtory of the Woman of <hi>Canaan; Mira re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> evangeliſta, mulier non mulier &amp;c.</hi> O wonderful! a woman and more then a woman! Troubles &amp; afflictions ſhe had, what Saint ever had not? indeed how could her vertue have been ſo bright and eminent without them. But her deportment under them was admirable, her truſt and confidence in God ſo ſtayed her up, that ſhe could be fervent and compoſ'd in he devotions, and chearful in her family, when the greateſt preſſures lay upon her; nay, to the former they did ever add vigour and activity. If at any time the waves came ſo thick upon her, that ſhe found her ſelf with <hi>Peter</hi> ready to ſink, ſhe quickly catch't hold of a ſure ſtay, and recovered her ſelf with <hi>David's</hi> reaſoning in the like extremity. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 43. <hi>ver. ult. Why art thou caſt down, O my ſoul! ſtill put thy truſt in God.</hi> The meditations of an holy man upon which place of Scripture ſhe very often had recourſe unto.<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Sibbs</hi> upon that text.</note> To haſten.</p>
            <p>There were two circumſtances about the death of this eminent Saint I muſt not omit. About a fortnight before ſhe dy'd, ſhe deſired the holy <hi>Sacrament</hi> at my hands, which I gave her the <hi>Sunday</hi> following; all the week before (notwithſtanding her great bodily weakneſs) with great devotion ſhe was preſent at the prayers of her family, and after that continued her attendance to the very laſt. This Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Banquet ſo refreſh'd her ſoul, that the joyes and ſatisfaction ſhe then poſſeſt were a happy anticipation, a delicious fore-taſte of that Heaven, from which ſhe was not to be long abſent: and here her good nature and Chriſtian Charity took an occaſion to expreſs it ſelf in being kindly angry with ſome of her Servants
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36596:13"/>for their neglect of that opportunity of coming to the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> and ſo not ſharing with her in ſo great a comfort and happineſs. She that had been a careful ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of the Lords day in her life, haſted early on that day to the celebration of an eternal Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath in the Heavens. In a word,<note place="margin">Departed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clock on ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day morning</note> as if in the language of <hi>David</hi> concerning God's houſe, ſhe had ſaid of her little <hi>Sanctuary: Here will I dwel, for I have a delight there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</hi> But a few hours before ſhe departed this life, ſhe was at prayers with the family at the Chappel, and I doubt not but after that in her greateſt Agonies and extremity, which laſted not very long, ſhe had pious Ejaculations and holy Soliloquies, her Lord found her ſo doing, and ſhe is now in poſſeſſion of the bleſſedneſs of the Text. Where let us leave her, and give me leave to addreſs my ſelf in two words,</p>
            <p n="1">I. To her near and dear Relations. I dare not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid you the ſhedding of ſome tears to the memory of ſo precious a Saint, and good a Mother, but I beg you to moderate them with your Chriſtian hopes. Your loſs is great, and truly ſo is mine, though I muſt not equal it, and ſo is her death to all that had the honour and happineſs of her acquaintance. But if you have one eye upon your loſs, let your other be upon her gain, her advantage, her happineſs; methinks ſhe beſpeaks you, <hi>Daughters weep not for me, but for your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and Children;</hi> and look upon her death not ſo much a loſs neither, as a ſhort privation of her compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; conſider her <hi>non amiſſam ſed praemiſſam;</hi> not loſt, only gone a little before to that Reſt we all labour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:36596:14"/>
            <p n="2">II. And to all that are here preſent, that knew her, let me beg you to let her memory be precious with you, let her vertues never dye, but be perſwaded to an imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of them, fix this great example continually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your eye. I conclude all with the exhortation of the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Finally, Brethren, whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt, whatſoever things are juſt, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report: if there be any vertue, and if there be any praiſe, think on theſe things and do them;</hi> that when our Lord ſhall come, he may find us <hi>ſo doing,</hi> and pronounce us bleſſed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:36596:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
